Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 7 -- Letters to Franklin 1783 January-November Mss.B.F85inventory07
American Philosophical Society
Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 7 -- Letters to Franklin
1783 January-November
Mss.B.F85inventory07
American Philosophical Society
1.0 section
This is part of the large inventory for the Benjamin Franklin Papers (Mss B F85). For complete information concerning this collection, please view the Collection Description.
832 items
Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Johonnot, Samuel Cooper. Geneva
    Scope and Contents note
    Account of his and Benny [Franklin Bache]'s success in their studies; prizes they will receive from the hands of the President of the College; hopes for peace and a speedy return to his native country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 1; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Steuben, Wilhelm Augustine von. Cüstrin
    Begs that the annexed letter may be forwarded to Congress; has already directed several in the same manner to his son, who is a general officer in the service of the United States, without receiving any answer; begs a line of explanantion from Dr. Franklin.
    English translation of the above.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Chester, André. Marseilles
    Enclosing a memoir and various certificates [5p.] from persons in authority, setting forth his zeal as English interpreter at Marseilles; his efforts to aid all Americans stranded in that port, and his desire and fitness for the position of American Consul at Marseilles. Requests Franklin to obtain a permit which will allow Charles Adam Duff to remain some time in Marseilles.
    (In French.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Moreau-Dufourneau, Jacob. Saint-Florentin
    Begging him to forward the enclosed reply to Lord George Fox whom he hears has left France for England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 2; A.L.S. 3p.; Corny, Dominique-Louis Ethis de
    Desiring to know if the American ship "Washington" has sailed; M. de Veimerange wishes information about it. He and Madame De Corny hope Franklin will choose an early date to drink tea with them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Crèvecoeur, St. Jean de
    Informing Franklin that certain records of the Province of New York were sent by Samuel Bayard on board an English ship and are now in the Tower of London; though useless to Great Britain now that peace is declared, believes they must be of great importance to New York. Congratulates Franklin on the happy issue and wishes him every blessing in the future.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Delamar, Mordÿay. Mogador
    Announcing that the American brig "Betsey" bound to Teneriffe was taken on the Barbary Coast by one of the privateers of the Emperor of Morocco and suspended with all her cargo; has received orders from the Emperor that, on the appearance of an Ambassador of the United States, the brig and cargo will be honorably discharged.
    (Press Copy.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Hillegas, Michael. Philadelphia
    Introducing William Wood, a connection of Franklin's old friend Mr. Thomas Bond and the Newbolds of New Jersey, who is endeavoring in a commercial way to increase his fortune. Reminds Franklin of Mr. Clarkson's request as to the possibility of obtaining a complete set of the Encyclopaedia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Barney, Capt Joshua. L'Orient
    Acknowledging Franklin's despatches with the money; expects to sail in the morning; sorry he could not carry the news of peace as expected.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Damboix, -----, fils
    One of five or six young men who desire to go to Boston and establish themselves in business; their families are poor and unable to furnish them with means to carry out their plan; desires to know if Congress offers any encouragement to would-be citizens.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 7; A.L.S. 3p.; Prost de Royer, Antoine-François. Lyon
    Read with delight the first laws drawn up by Franklin for Pennsylvania; sends him the first two volumes of his "Dictionnaire de Jurisprudence et des Arrets "; refers him to certain articles which he thinks may prove specially interesting.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Grammont, -----, marquis de. Paris
    Desiring Franklin to name a time when he may have the pleasure of an interview.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1738 January 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Hill, Charles and James. Bordeaux
    Reminding him of his promise to give them a letter of recommendation to some of his friends in Philadelphia or Boston provided he received a letter from Dr. Thomas Percival, certifying on their identity; enclosing Dr. Percival's letter [1p.] as well as one from their brother Joseph Hill, of Manchester [1p.]; have taken their passage on the American ship "Minerva."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Hodgson, William. London
    Positive orders from the Admiralty for all American prisoners to be sent to Morlaix, where they wish the English prisoners to be awaiting them; hopes something will occur to clear Congress of having refused to comply with the agreement made in England for the exchange of Lieut.-Col. Tarleton, Simcoc and Capt. MacLean, for whom they will release any officers in New York. Desires the earliest intelligence of the ultimatum.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 8; L. 1p.; Hodgson, William. London
    Has been at the Secretary's Office relative to the exchange of prisoners; the Admiralty ordered vessels to depart immediately with all American prisoners; these prisoners are to be sent to Morlaix where he desires Dr. Franklin to send the English prisoners.
    (Press copy of an extract.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    Thomas Connelly, an American taken prisoner by a Guernsey corsair on his passage from l'Orient to Philadelphia; his escape from an English prison and his arrival in France; advanced him a certain sum of money on Franklin's account.
    A. E. by Dr. Franklin. Give him five louis, taking his notes, etc., and direct him to go via Orleans.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Sending enclosed, letters to Lord Shelburne and Mr. Vaughan; thinks the subject worth a national claim; begs Franklin to add a line to his letter to Lord Shelburne.
    - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 9; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Pio, Luigi de
      Sending Franklin a letter arrived from Naples.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Chapel, Jacques. Valencicnnes
    Will send him certain samples of his manufactures which he begs may be sent with Franklin's recommendation to the the most reputable merchants in America and to American manufacturers in certain French towns; when peace is declared, desires the position of paymaster.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 11; A.L.S. 2p.; D'ron, -----. Nantes
    Concerning a debt owing him by one Fritz Sellier who left for Boston and has not since been heard from; begs for information of his present whereabouts.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 12; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Sandoz-Rollins, Daniel Alfons von. Paris
    Sends the subjoined memoir of the Maritime Society of Prussia; hopes he will read and answer it to prove that he has fulfilled his commission.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Writes on behalf of M. [Louis] de Boislandry, merchant of L'Aigle, who desires an interview with Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Laskowski, Josephus Corabita de. Galicia
    Begs Franklin to procure him a suitable and remunerative occupation in America.
    ( In Latin.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 13; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Grubb, Richard. Paris
    Desiring a passport for England via Calais.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Servin, Antoine-Nicolas. Rouen
    Hopes to wait on him in Paris with a copy of his work [de la Legislature Criminelle]; desired to bring out especially the vices of the criminal legislation of England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 16; L.S. 2p.; Vergennes, Charles Gravier, comte de. Versailles
    Sending him a copy of a memoir from Messrs. Faure, Donneau and Co., of Marseilles, owners of the ship "L'Élégante"; Franklin has been fully informed of the details of this affair and can therefore judge of the justice of the demand for indemnity; begs Franklin to use his influence to procure this firms their just dues; thinks it unjust that French merchants should be the unfortunate victims of such reprehensible conduct as that of the commander of the militia at "Carlerscreck."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Fraguier, Mme Nicolas-Ambroise. Paris
    Sending the enclosed memoir [1p.] from le Sieur Nivière, who desires to obtain the post of Consul at Lyons; a man of merit.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 16; A.L.S. 3p.; Penide, -----. Lyons
    Concerning a plan on the part of himself and two others to establish a silk manufactory in America; desires his advice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Curson, Samuel. Marseilles
    Wishes to know if an American will be permitted to establish a business house in Lisbon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Appée, Léonard. Paris
    Preferring his claim for three months' wages and his share of the prize-money during his service as a volunteer on board the American frigate "Providence" in the fall of 1778; enclosing a letter from Louvel [1p.], Agent at Paimboeuf, certifying his statements.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Reasons why he has not been to Passy; begs Franklin to name a day when he will dine with Madame Le Roy and himself.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 17; L.S. 2p.; Houdetot, Comtesse d'
    Inconsolable at missing Franklin's visit; desired greatly to see him and congratulate him on the happy peace; requests his and his grandson's presence at a musicale she gives on the 30th.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 19; A.L.S. 3p.; Faujas de Saint-Fond, Barthélemy. Paris
    Sending a specimen of the new metal, used for sheathing vessels; description of the nails which it is fastened. Sending also a curious stone found in Sicily; use made of it by the inhabitants; process by which the bitumen is removed; enclosing another copy of his work on "La Pouzzolane" which he begs may be sent to the person in charge of the ports of public works in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Gastellier, René-Georges. Montargis
    Thanks him for accepting the dedication of his work; will comply with the conditions dictated by Franklin's modesty and delicacy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 20; A.L.S. 4p.; Backhaus, Jean Guillaume. Hanover
    Enclosing a memoir [4p.] which he begs Franklin to place before the Congress with a favorable recommendation; the advantages of a commercial alliance between Germany and America; superior position of Hamburg as a residence for an accredited agent of the United States; applies for such a position.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 20; A.L.S. 3p.; Millet, -----. Paris
    Concerning a bill for groceries bought by M. Duchemin for Dr. Franklin's use.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 20; A.L.S. 3p.; Garos, Louis-Julien. Fontenay-le-Comte
    Writes on behalf of Frenchman, le Sieur François Gray [?] who deserted his regiment in France, and took up his residence in Philadelphia; certain sums due him by inheritance which the Government thinks he should forfeit as a deserter; begs Franklin to procure his pardon from the French Government in order that he may enter into possession of his just inheritance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Duviquet, abbé Pierre. Paris
    Offering his verses in honor of the peace; placed Franklin's name beside those of Louis XVI and de Vergennes; enumerates Franklin's great achievements.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 22; L.S. 3p.; Trout, Joseph (prisoner). Niort Castle
    Natives of Massachusetts and followers of the sea; taken prisoners by an English privateer and carried into New York, where they were kept eight months on board a prison ship and then sent to England; on their arrival, they chose, rather than go on board a man-of-war or into prison, to take passage on board a vessel bound for the West Indies; this ship captured by a French man-of-war; in spite of being Americans they were conveyed to a French prison; begs Franklin to obtain their release.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Caffiéri, Jean Jacques
    Franklin's country knows how to appreciate his great services; in case America should desire to leave to posterity a monument to this glorious event or one to those patriots who have sacrificed their lives in the cause, begs Franklin to employ his talents.
    (In French)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Gebhard, -------. Strasbourg
    Begging Franklin to forward the enclosed letter to his father.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Brongniart, Alexandre Théodore. Paris
    Sending two new proofs of the medal; points out certain imperfections which will be corrected. Reminds Franklin of his promise to tell him what should be written on the lower part of the medal.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 23; A.L.S. 2p.; La Salle, M de
    Writes on behalf of M. Poulletier, of Paris, who desires a letter of recommendation for his son whom he is about to send to Philadelphia with a quantity of Merchandise; this request seconded by la Marquise Deroillers. On the fifth of May their lodge gave a fête at which Franklin promised to be plresent.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 24; A.L.S. 1p.; La Touche-Tréville, comte de. Paris
    Congratulating Franklin on the independence of the United states and sending him the annexed letter forwarded from London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Bache, Sarah. Philadelphia
    As soon as his letter by Miss [S.] Beckwith was received, she and Mr. Bache waited on her and requested her to stay with them till she could be agreeably settled; promises that she shall never want warm friends in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Smith, Jacob. Mill Prison
    Describing the wretched condition of his fellow prisoners; the French, Dutch and Spanish receive clothes and money, but the poor Americans are given nothing; there are 160 men all told and one half are without shoes and stockings.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 24; A.L.S. 4p.; Perrault, -----. Deux-ponts
    Desires to become a citizen of the United States, and to find some useful employment; begs Franklin to put him in the way of obtaining his passage over.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Martineau, L. Bordeaux
    Concerning his project of establishing a sugar-refinery at Philadelphia; desires to know if Congress will defray certain expenses and grant certain liberties.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    His father staying with him; expects to wait on Franklin shortly. Acknowledging his note to Lord Shelburne. Just received the news of peace.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing his friend Major Samuel White, who is in the business of obtaining passports for the American ships outward bound.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Hodgson, William
    Desiring to know if one of his letters containing a bill of exchange came safely to hand.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Hodgson, William. London
    Waited on the Secretary of State with the discharge of the officers, and obtained his consent for the cartel vessel to go to l'Orient. Congratulating him on the glorious and honorable termination of the war. Reminds him of his promise to sketch out the wisest and best conduct for England to pursue with respect to America, after independence is acknowledged. Desires to enter into commercial relations with America; wishes a pass for his vessel called the "Mary," and begs Mr. W[illiam] T[emple] Franklin to procure him one from the Spanish and French Ministers; apprehensions of her being captured before hostilities finally cease.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Fanning, Nathaniel. Dunkirk Gaol
    Advised not to desist in his petition to Franklin, who can procure him his enlargement; can prove that he is a native of New London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de
    Sending Franklin his congratulations and those of the Comtesse de Forbach on the approaching peace. A few lines of affection and admiration in the Countess's hand.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Charles Gilibert and Co. Lyons
    Concerning a letter received from Mr. John Hoskins Stone, merchant in Annapolis, Md., with an invoice of goods; desire to know if they may place confidence in this gentleman and execute his orders.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 28; A.L.S. 4p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Account of an experiment in electricity; desires to dedicate his work to Franklin; has received a request from the Great Duke of Russia for a copy of the French edition and the German translation. Desires information of a machine which raises water by means of a rope. Begs Franklin to look over the letters of a Mr. Valltravers who is in desperate need of some employment. Advice how to treat his attacks of gout; published in Latin some years before a dissertation on how to treat gout, gravel, etc., translated from Dr. [Nathaniel] Hulme; 1 explains his theory. Attitude of England towards his country; England's policy in granting independence to America is to better crush France.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition note
    Printed, in part, in Hale's Franklin in France, II, 254.
    General note
    [Nieuwe, veilige en gemaklijke manier, om den steen (etc.). Rotterdam, 1778.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Grasse, François-Joseph-Paul, comte de. Paris
    Congratulates Franklin on the signing of the preliminaries of peace, and on the independence of America; encloses a letter of congratulation to the President of Congress; hopes this proof of his attachment to America will be as acceptable as the one he rendered at Yorktown. Wishes to send him also one of his memoirs on the naval battle of April 12th to prove his blamelessness in the affair.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 28; A.L.S. 4p.; Kümmel, Adam Christian. Brieg
    Sends him nine treatises on the valuation of gold coins throughout the states of Europe; has fifty-three more treatises which he will send also if Franklin desires it; has been engaged on this work for twenty-five or thirty years; believes this knowledge of the comparative values of various moneys will probably be of great advantage to a growing commercial power like America; applies to Franklin to render him assistance to get his works printed.
    (In German.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Desires to know if the prohibition on English goods in America ceases with the declaration of peace; also, if tobacco already imported into France will be received in England. Questions of returning to England the few prisoners still in Nantes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 29; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Garthshore, Dr. Maxwell. Paris
    Expressing great regret at being obliged to leave Paris without paying his respects to Franklin; except on one occasion which, owing to the drunkenness of his coachman, was at a very improper hour.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 29; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Vaughan, Benjamin and Samuel. Paris
    Regretting their inability to accept his invitation for Sunday. Enclose a list of books which they desire returned.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Pettit, Gen Charles. Philadelphia
    Recommending to Franklin's notice his son, Andrew Pettit.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 29; L in 3d P. 1p.; Nevill, ---- and ----- Moore
    From Ireland; ask permission to pay their respects to him before leaving Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Barclay, Thomas. L'Orient
    Congratulating him on the independence of America. Desires passports from the British Minister so that several American vessels in the harbor may sail without delay; gives a list of the ships; all carry public supplies; importance of getting them to America before the shipments from England arrive.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Jay, John. Paris
    Desires to know if Franklin can provide for the payment of Mr. Johnson's bills, in case he accepts them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 30; L.S. 2p.; Meyronnet de Saint-Marc, chevalier de. Lisbon
    The Vice-Consul of France at the Island of Fayal, desires reimbursement for expenses he incurred on behalf of five Americans whom he sent back to their native country; mentions the names of people in Passy at whose houses he had the pleasure of meeting Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 30; L.S. 2p.; Lafreté, Angélique-Michéle-Rosalie Jogues de Martinville. Paris
    M. de Labarre, desires to go to America under Franklin's protection; M. and Mme. la Vicomtesse de la Herreria are much interested in him; trusts Franklin will oblige them in this matter. Her health still delicate; begs Franklin to come and see her.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Wets, Jean Guild. Bruges
    Intention of their firm to sent some vessels to America for the purposes of trade; apply to Franklin for some information, especially as to the name of trustworthy American firms.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 31; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing the Hon. John Wheelock, President of Dartmouth College, who has come to Europe to obtain donations for an institution of learning.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 31; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Brongniart, Alexandre Théodore. Paris
    Desiring to know if he received two new proofs of the medal, as well as that with the head of liberty; reminding him that he has not yet stated what he desires engraved at each side.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    Recommending to Franklin President Wheelock and his brother.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 31; A.L.S. 3p.; Illens, ----- de. Marseilles
    Hope of obtaining the considerable sum due him from South Carolina; now that peace has been declared, hopes America will satisfy the creditors who came to her aid in time of trouble; desires to know whether the debt will be paid in goods or land.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January 31; A.L.S. 2p.; Veuve d’Aubremé and Sons. Brussels
    Congratulating him on the independence of America, and his glorious part in the great event. Their desire to establish commercial relations with America; if this plan is practicable, begs Franklin to recommend some firm in Boston or Philadelphia to whom they can consign their vessels.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January; N. in 3d P. 1p.; St. Olympe, -----, chevalier de. Paris
    Thanks Franklin for lending him Abbé Raynal's book which he read with interest. Will return Abbé Raynal's letter to Franklin in a few days.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 January; Mem. 2p.; -----, -----. Passy
    Proposition for furnishing table supplies and catering for Dr. Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 February 1; L.S. 2p.; Boyer, -----. Bordeaux